Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is צח. tzaddik-chet. We
pick up with the משנה mishnah at the bottom of צז עמוד
ב. tzaddik-zayin amud-bet. And here we go.
מכרה כתובתה מקצתה. makhra kesuvatah miktzatah. So now we're dealing with the
issue about the widow's collecting her כתובה kesuvah and the fact that
she's also supported by the estate. את תהא ניזונת בביתי כל ימי
מיגר אלמנותיך, at tehi nizonet bevaiti kol yemei maggar almanutayikh, you should
be supported like fed from my estate as long as you're during
the period of your widowhood until it's time for her to collect
her כתובה. kesuvah. There's a whole interesting discussion whether whether it's her
option to decide to get her כתובה kesuvah paid out or whether
the heirs can do it whenever they want. Anyway but that's the
basic scenario here that we're dealing with is the אלמנה almanah collecting
her כתובה. kesuvah. So and the again the tradeoff or the triggering
of when she starts collecting when she collects her כתובה kesuvah that
she stops being able to get supported from the estate. So the
משנה mishnah says, מכרה כתובתה מקצתה, makhra kesuvatah miktzatah, if she sells
her כתובה kesuvah or even part of it,
משכנה כתובתה מקצתה, mashkanah kesuvatah miktzatah, if she collateralized her כתובה—oh, kesuvah
that was a good use of the verb there—if she collateralized her
כתובה kesuvah or a part of it, נתנה כתובתה לאחר או מקצתה,
nasanah kesuvatah le-acher o miktzatah, or she gives it as a gift
or part of it, לא תמכור השאר אלא בבית דין. lo timkor
hash'ar ela beveit din. Then she cannot sell the remainder of it
except with the court because here also becomes the issue about her
ability to sell off the estate in order to
have her get the—thank you—what's owed to her paid. And the question
is for which type of a debt. So what we saw in
the previous משנה mishnah was the position that she can do it
for for what do you call it? Certainly she can do it
for מזונות mezonot because every time she needs to get fed, she
doesn't have to go running to בית דין beit din and have
בית דין beit din sell off a part of the estate. However,
there's a debate about whether she also is entitled to do this
for the basic payment of the כתובה kesuvah because of you know
this משום חינא mishum khina in order to make it more seemly
or less unseemly for women to have to be handling that type
of stuff always through the court. Okay. So this משנה mishnah is
going like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who says she can only sell
off the estate to pay for the מזונות, mezonot, not for the
base כתובה. kesuvah. Number one. And the number two assumption is is
that as soon as she begins to get a payout of even
part of the כתובה, kesuvah, she no longer gets מזונות. mezonot. Okay?
So those are the two assumptions. Number one, the only thing she
can sell off without a בית דין beit din is for the
מזונות. mezonot. And number two is she can't get the מזונות mezonot
once she gets a partial payout for the כתובה. kesuvah. One second.
So if she begins to get a whole but even a partial
payout for the כתובה, kesuvah, that's the first part of the משנה,
mishnah, then she has she can't sell the rest except through the
court because anything now that she'll be selling will be she's selling
for the base כתובה—I kesuvah mean for the כתובה, kesuvah, not for
the מזונות—and mezonot therefore and since she's selling for the כתובה kesuvah
not the מזונות, mezonot, she needs to sell it through the court.
The משנה's mishnah a little misleading because even the initial sale if
it's done to pay out the כתובה kesuvah has to be through
the court, right? Because this is רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. But okay.
What it means is she's been selling in order to get her
מזונות mezonot bill paid, to get her food bill paid. Now as
soon as—so she's been doing that for the last five years—as soon
as she begins to get a payout for the כתובה kesuvah itself,
now any sale has to be through the court. But the bigger
point really is is that now she stops getting מזונות mezonot and
now she can only get a payout for the remainder of the
כתובה kesuvah and that has to be through the court. What?
How do you see all that in it?
I don't. It's not clear. But that's, you know, but that's sort
of how the גמרא's Gemara going to explain it. Yes.
Wait, she sells off some of the כתובה kesuvah for מזונות. mezonot.
Mm-hmm.
So
let's say that money runs out. She could sell a little bit
more for
מזונות. mezonot. Yeah. But let's say she sells some for מזונות, mezonot,
that money then runs out, she doesn't want to sell more for
more מזונות. mezonot. Do the heirs then—are their heirs are obligated to
provide מזונות mezonot at that moment? No.
What do you mean she doesn't want to sell more? How does
she want to get paid for her מזונות? mezonot?
There's no—there's no other obligation for anyone else to provide מזונות. mezonot.
No. She just wants the heirs to just like give her food,
let's say.
What do you mean, from the מטלטלין? metaltelin? You mean that's your
question, whether she wants it to be from the קרקע karka or
from the מטלטלין? metaltelin? Yeah. Well I mean she's gotta be paid
from something. Some part of the estate has to pay. It's not
coming from the heirs' own pocket.
Right. So nobody has the obligation to provide the מזונות mezonot for
her.
She only has a right to get that payment out of the
estate. Right. Okay. All right. So I mean there's that whole question—there
is that question about whether it's from the קרקע karka or even
from the מטלטלין metaltelin for the מזונות. mezonot. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: וחכמים אומרים—now vachachamim omrim that's presumably as
a continuation of רבי Rabbi שמעון—וחכמים אומרים, מוכרת היא אפילו ארבעה וחמישה
פעמים. mocheret hi afilu arbaah vachamishah peamim. She can sell even four
or five times, which means that the you know repeating their position
basically that the—you know, that the sale even for the כתובה kesuvah
itself does not require to be in בית דין. beit din. So
even if she's collecting her כתובה kesuvah piecemeal, whenever she sells in
order to get paid for the כתובה, kesuvah, she doesn't need a
בית דין. beit din. ומוכרת מזונות שלא בבית דין. umocheret mezonot shelo
beveit din.
And she can continue... you to sell for מזונות mizonos without a
בית דין. beis din.
Again, that is not רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon obviously רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon, also agrees מוכרת למזונות שלא בבית דין. moches limizonos shelo be-beis
din. But presumably the point they're saying is that even once the
כתובה kesubah began to be paid out, she can continue
to still sell the property for the purpose of מזונות. mizonos. Okay
as long as she's not fully paid out, exactly. הכותבת למזונות מכרתי.
Ha-kosesves limizonos macharti.
And then she writes and we discussed this before what's the purpose
of writing that was a complicated דף daf before, but then she
writes basically on it like she writes on the note line of
the check, this was for מזונות, mizonos, and the גמרא Gemara discussed
before what that purpose that served. I'm not going to review that.
וגרושה לא תמכור אלא בבית דין. U'gerusha lo simchor ela be-beis din.
But a גרושה gerusha have to sell only with a בית דין
beis din and the explanation for this was that the reason the
אלמנה almanah does not have to sell for the בית דין beis
din when she's getting the base כתובה kesubah is this issue that
the husband wouldn't want his widow to have to go through that.
But given that this is not his wife, this is his divorced
wife, then he doesn't matter so she's got to in this case
sell through בית דין beis din and she's selling only for the
כתובה kesubah itself clearly not for the מזונות mizonos because it's a
case of a גרושה. gerusha. So again to repeat what the basic
point of this משנה Mishnah is is that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
says that she sells only for the מזונות mizonos that the only
time she does not need a בית דין beis din is if
she selling for the מזונות. mizonos. And רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon also
says that if she's even getting part of the כתובה kesubah paid
out she stops getting מזונות. mizonos. So once part of the כתובה
kesubah is paid out from this point on number one she can't
get מזונות mizonos and number two therefore any sale for the base
כתובה kesubah have to be through a בית דין. beis din. And
the חכמים Chachamim reject both positions. Number one is that she doesn't
need a בית דין beis din even for the base כתובה. kesubah.
And number two even when part of the כתובה kesubah is paid
out as long as it's not the whole כתובה kesubah she can
continue to get מזונות. mizonos. So therefore if she sells part of
the כתובה kesubah she continues to get מזונות mizonos and so she
number one and number two she does not need a בית דין
beis din whether she's selling for מזונות mizonos or whether she's selling
for the remainder of the כתובה kesubah until the full כתובה kesubah
is paid out. Okay so let's take a look now at the
גמרא. Gemara.
Rabbi yes sorry just for something like really basic that's eluding me
here. She's selling off from מזונות mizonos she's selling off from she's
selling
property
that's hers anyway to sell correct?
No she's selling off from the heir's estate from the estate that
the heirs inherited. Okay. So
doesn't have
to be her property right?
She's not selling her property. She can do whatever she wants with
her property. Now what she is selling to get the כתובה kesubah
paid out then she is selling to get her property back. That
is true correct. Okay so let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. מתניתין מני רבי שמעון היא. Masnisin mani Rebbi Shimon hi. Our
משנה Mishnah is רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon דתניא detanya מכר כתובתה משכן
כתובתה עשה כתובתה אפותיקי. machar kesubasah mishkan kesubasah asah kesubasah apotiki.
Sold her כתובה kesubah collateralized it made it an אפותיקי apotiki which
basically means that she took a loan out from somebody else and
she took she took a mortgage essentially out on the property that
was gonna be for her כתובה. kesubah. לאחר אין לה מזונות. le-acher
ein lah mizonos.
She no longer gets מזונות. mizonos. And that's either תנא קמא סתם
Tanna Kamma stam or it's רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir but she doesn't
get מזונות mizonos when it's the whole כתובה kesubah that is basically
now collected or effectively collected. רבי שמעון אומר אף על פי שלא
מכר ולא משכן כתובתה אלא מחציתה. Rebbi Shimon omer af al pi
shelo machar v'lo mishkan kesubasah ela machsisah. Even if she only sold
or collateralized part of her כתובה kesubah literally half. אבדה מזונותיה. avdah
mizonoseha. She lost her מזונות. mizonos. Okay
so the basic issue number one before whether you need a בית
דין beis din or not is the bigger issue of whether she
is entitled to continue collecting מזונות mizonos according to the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma until she fully gets the payout of her כתובה kesubah
and according to רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon once she even began to
get the payout of the כתובה. kesubah. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this. למימרא דרבי שמעון סבר דלא אמרינן מקצת כסף ככל כסף.
L'meimra de-Rebbi Shimon savar delo amrinan miksas kesef k'chol kesef. This seems
to say that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is of the opinion that
we don't say part of the money is like all of the
money. And of course logically you'd say what? It sounds like the
opposite. It sounds like רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is saying that once
she got a partial payout it's like she got a full payout.
So the question is always is the glass half empty or half
full? Which part are you looking at? So the גמרא Gemara says
we're talking about the part that she has left to collect. Okay
so מקצת כסף ככל כסף miksas kesef k'chol kesef means as long
as there is some money left to collect it's like the כתובה
kesubah debt is still outstanding. Okay got that? מקצת כסף ככל כסף
Miksas kesef k'chol kesef means not when you've received a little you've
received a lot but if there's still some part you haven't received
it's like you have not yet got paid yet for it okay.
So רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon holds that as long as לא אמרינן
מקצת כסף ככל כסף. lo amrinan miksas kesef k'chol kesef. We don't
say that as long as there's some money left to be paid
out it's like the כתובה kesubah debt is still outstanding. No the
כתובה kesubah debt is not outstanding anymore and she does not get
מזונות. mizonos. ורבנן סברי V'rabbanan savri and the Rabbis hold אמרינן מקצת
כסף ככל כסף. amrinan miksas kesef k'chol kesef. We say as long
as there is some money left to be paid out it's like
all of the money still all of the debt remains outstanding and
therefore she still continues to get מזונות. mizonos. Okay so the גמרא
Gemara says האיפכא שמעינן להו. ha-ipcha shaminun lehu. We heard that they
held the exact opposite. This has got to be one of the
most bizarre analogies the גמרא's Gemara about to make. דתניא detanya והוא
אשה בבתוליה יקח. ve-hu ishah b'visuleha yikach. Right
you got it okay from this week's פרשה parsha last week's פרשה.
parsha. He
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol must take a woman in her virginity.
So what's בבתוליה? b'visuleha? פרט לבוגרת שכלו בתוליה דברי רבי מאיר. Prat
le-vugeres she-kalu visuleha divrei Rebbi Meir. This excludes the case of a
woman who has reached the
age of puberty end That woman does not have the hymen is
not fully intact. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. And a
כהן גדול kohein gadol cannot marry her because the hymen is not
as presumably thick as it was before the period of puberty. רבי
אליעזר ורבי שמעון מכשירין בבוגרת. Rabbi Eliezer veRabbi Shimon machshirin bevogeres. רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon say that's okay, he
can still marry her. So you see that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
holds that as long as some of the hymen is gone, it's
like the whole hymen is gone. And רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer hold as long as some of the hymen
is still there, it's like the whole hymen is there, which of
course directly translates into the question about whether the entire כתובה kesuvah
has been paid out or not. Of course one cannot, of course
this has got to be one of the most
absurd analogies ever. Of course what it really does is it reminds
you though that the amount of the כתובה kesuvah is the מוהר
mohar is a price paid and it is a מוהר mohar for
בתולות, besulos, right? So the standard amount is the price paid for
a woman who is,
for the price of the virginity essentially. So there does seem to
be an interesting analogy, what? Meaning if a woman is a בתולה,
besulah, right? According to the תורה Torah the bride price is two
hundred. If she's not a בתולה, besulah, the תורה Torah doesn't have
any bride price at all. Bride price? It's not in the תורה.
Torah. Right, in the תורה. Torah. Exactly. Well, the תורה Torah doesn't
have it as a כתובה kesuvah either, the תורה Torah I mean
it might have been negotiated but there certainly was a socially standardized
price.
Okay, but we're talking about collecting your כתובה. kesuvah. Yeah. We're talking
about collecting something that's already been pre-established.
Well, there was a default, but then you could make it flexible
and certainly you could add to it and that was the whole
idea of the תוספת tosefes and also it had to do with
how much of the dowry she brought in and all those things.
But it starts with the biblical idea of the bride price which
wasn't even a כתובה kesuvah which was money paid up front. So
there is an interesting analogy here, to the degree you continue to
consider the כתובה kesuvah bride price, so if there's a partial כתובה
kesuvah that hasn't been paid off, that's sort of like well, partial
כתובה kesuvah is equal to like partial virginity, you know? So he
married her why would there be a partial כתובה? kesuvah? A partial
כתובה kesuvah would reflect reality of a woman being a partial virgin.
So there seems to be exactly. So anyway, it's a bizarre comparison,
but it seems to be reminding us of that source of the
idea of כתובה. kesuvah.
Yeah, and how the חכמים chachamim transformed the bride price into a
kind of insurance policy for after the marriage so to speak. There's
a deep
echo. Exactly.
Exactly. Exactly. So the גמרא Gemara wants to say oh look so
it sounds like if there's if part of it is there, it's
still there is the position of the חכמים chachamim but here it's
the position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who says she's still a
בתולה. besulah. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, no, התם hasham
says the גמרא Gemara בקרא פליגי. bikra pligi. There that's not a
general debate of whether we consider something partly there still there. That's
a specific debate of how do we read a verse. רבי מאיר
סבר בתולה, Rabbi Meir savar besulah, as the verse says והוא אשה
בבתוליה, vehu isha bivsuleha, בתולה besulah by itself would have meant אפילו
מקצת בתולים, afilu mikzas besulim, even if the woman is just a
partial בתולה. besulah. בבתוליה, bivsuleha,
so the formulation of the word like that, her בתולים, besulim, why
is it sort of underscoring, why is it saying it with that
expanded form? עד דאיכא כולהו בתולים. ad de'ika kulu bivsulim.
That's to say that the entire בתולים besulim have to be there.
So if only partial part is missing, he can't marry her. בבתוליה,
bivsuleha, now what's the בית? beis? So כדרכה אין שלא כדרכה לא.
ke'darkah in she'lo ke'darkah lo.
That it's only a problem if she has had vaginal sex not
anal sex because again רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir makes sense, he is
focused very much on the hymen, not on whether she has had
sexual activity or not. Not whether she's had sex, but on the
hymen, right? Because if she's invalid even if she just passed puberty,
it's about the full presence of the hymen. So ironically, if this
woman had anal sex, so even though she is not a virgin
in terms of her sexual activity, but her hymen is fully intact,
that's okay for a כהן גדול kohein gadol to marry. He can't
marry her after puberty but he can marry her if she's had
sex without it being vaginal sex. Okay, that is what רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says. רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון סברי בתולה שלמה משמע. Rabbi
Eliezer veRabbi Shimon savri besulah sheleimah mashma.
No, the word בתולה besulah means the full בתולה besulah is, she's
a complete בתולה, besulah, the hymen is fully intact. בבתוליה, bivsuleha, that
now changed form means אפילו מקצת בתולים, afilu mikzas besulim, even if
there's only a partial hymen he still is allowed to marry her.
Meaning after puberty. בבתוליה, bivsuleha, שכל בתוליה קיימין בין כדרכה בין שלא
כדרכה. she-hukal bivsuleha kayamin bein ke'darkah bein she'lo ke'darkah.
But the בבתוליה bivsuleha means she has to be a full virgin
meaning it doesn't matter whether it's anal or vaginal, which basically translates
into the fact that they focus not on the hymen but they
focus on whether she has had sex or not. So if she's
had sex, I don't care anal or vaginal, she's not a virgin,
but if she's reached puberty and the hymen is thinner or whatever,
she's past puberty, it doesn't matter she still is a virgin. So
bottom line רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir focuses on the physical hymen and
they focus much more on whether she's had sex or not. Anyway,
the גמרא Gemara says that's just based on a local debate of
reading the verse, it doesn't tell you a general issue of whether
you say partial if something is partially there is it like it's
all there or not. Okay, so now we continue. That was quite
a fascinating comparison. little comparison.
And you didn't even bring up יחזקאל's Yechezkel version.
Thank you. So anyway, the גמרא Gemara says, so anyway, we've got
this debate about whether when a woman gets partly paid out, does
she continue to collect מזונות. mezonot. ההיא איתתא, Hahi iteta, now a
story, there was a woman דתפסה כסא דכספא בכתובתה. detapsa kasa dechaspa
bichtuvtah.
She seized a cup of silver for payment of her כתובה. ketubah.
Okay, now it did not have the full payment and she did
this to collect her base כתובה, ketubah, her כתובה ketubah payout, this
was not for מזונות. mezonot. תבעה מזוני, Tava’ah mezoni,
now she wanted to still get paid for the מזונות. mezonot.
אתו לקמיה דרבא, Ato lekamei deRava, they came before Rava. אמר להו,
Amar lehu, he said to the orphans, יתמי, yasmi, זילו הבו לה
מזונות, zilu havu lah mezonot, go continue to pay her מזונות. mezonot.
She has not had her whole כתובה ketubah paid out, we go
like the חכמים Chachamim against רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon and continue to
pay her מזונות. mezonot. לית דחש לה לדרבי שמעון, Leis dechash lah
lediRabbi Shimon,
nobody is concerned for Rabbi Shimon's position until the whole כתובה ketubah
is paid out, she continues to get מזונות. mezonot. דאמר לאו מינה
מקצת כסף ככל הכסף, De’amar lav minah mikzat kesef kechol hakesef, we
don't go like Rabbi Shimon who says partial is like the full,
no as long as partial כתובה ketubah remains the full כתובה ketubah
remains. Now of course the interesting thing would be would be that
if she is that if we פסקן-ed pasken like the earlier discussion
that it's at their discretion to pay her out, then if they
wanted to stop paying מזונות mezonot they should just pay her the
balance, okay, but presumably that would maybe might be their choice, but
they would rather not pay the מזונות mezonot and not pay the
balance. Now they're forced to choose. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. שלח ליה רבא בריה דרבא לרב יוסף, Shelach lei
Rava brei deRava leRav Yosef, so Rava the son of Rava sent
to Rav Yosef, מוכרת שלא בבית דין צריכה שבועה או אינה צריכה
שבועה. mocheret shelo beveit din tzerichah shevuah o einah tzerichah shevuah. If
a woman goes ahead and she's selling the property without going to
the court, right, which she's entitled to do, certainly for מזונות, mezonot,
possibly even for the כתובה ketubah itself, that was the debate of
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, does she
need to make a שבועה shevuah to the orphans that she has
not had her debt, you know, she's not had it paid out
already? Okay, now תוספות Tosafot of course asks the question, I'll just
show you the first line in תוספות, Tosafot, מוכרת שלא בבית דין
צריכה שבועה, mocheret shelo beveit din tzerichah shevuah, ואם תאמר, ve’im tomar,
says תוספות, Tosafot, what do you mean we've been discussing this for
a while, מתניתין היא בפרק הכונס, matnitin hi beperek hachones, דתנן אין
אלמנה נפרעת מנכסי יתומים אלא בשבועה. detnan ein almanah nifra’at minechasei yetomim
ela bishvuah. Okay, and then he goes on to have a whole
lot of questions about this. All right, so we won't but anyway,
so there is this question don't we always say that she needs
a כתובה, ketubah, a שבועה, shevuah, but here let's see what where
the גמרא Gemara goes with this. Does she need a שבועה shevuah
when she's coming and she's selling it without going to the court?
Okay, she's just selling it on her own, right? She has pretty
free rein of the orphans' estate. Man, if I were the orphans,
I would want to, you know, pull this in a little bit,
I'd like to get control over this situation. And what maybe what
I would do if I were the orphans is I would sell
like you know, like a $10,000, put it in escrow, you know,
have her draw on that, I wouldn't want her to סתם stam
start selling off the estate whenever she needed to get her כתובה
ketubah paid, you know, whenever she get her מזונות mezonot paid. Okay,
so that's what the גמרא's Gemara sort of trying to figure out.
She's got all this latitude, do we have some control over it?
Does she have to make a שבועה? shevuah? So let's take a
look. So מוכרת
צריכה שבועה אינה צריכה שבועה. mocheret tzerichah shevuah einah tzerichah shevuah. ותיבעי
ליה הכרזה. Veti’ba’ei leih hachrazah. גמרא Gemara says, why don't you ask
if we need to make a public announcement, like take out an
ad in the newspaper, because here this woman is selling without going
through the court system, okay, so maybe she's going to way undersell
the property, right, maybe you need a system that before she sells
it she takes out some ads and some public announcements to ensure
that if it's being auctioned off it fetches a good price. So
why aren't you asking about that? Okay, that's not a question about
whether the debt's been paid but it's to protect the interests of
the orphans. So the גמרא Gemara says ותיבעי ליה הכרזה. veti’ba’ei leih
hachrazah. So אמר ליה, amar leih, he said back, הכרזה לא קמיבעיא
לי, hachrazah lo kamiba’aya li, I don't have any question about the
issue about making a public announcement, you know, that there's going to
be an auction of the estate. דאמר רבי זירא אמר רב נחמן
אלמנה ששמה לעצמה לא עשתה ולא כלום. de’amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rav
Nachman almanah sheshamah le’atzmah lo asata velo chelum.
If the widow basically evaluates the property, assesses, that's a better word,
assesses the property for her own sake. She says, oh this Ferrari?
Yeah, I'd say a thousand bucks. Okay, and then she sells it
to herself. Okay,
so then it's לא עשתה ולא כלום, lo asata velo chelum, right?
She cannot assess it for herself while she's selling off the property
to raise money for her מזונות. mezonot. לא עשתה ולא כלום. Lo
asata velo chelum. Now היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case? אי
דאכריז, Ei de’achriz, if there's been a public ads and announcements and
it's being, you know, and other people have a chance to bid
on it, so אמאי לא עשתה ולא כלום, amai lo asata velo
chelum, why did she not do anything? You know, why I mean
why does it make a difference whether she's selling it to another
person or selling it to herself if the announcements have gone out
and everybody has had a chance to bid on it and she
has the highest bid, right, so then
but who's controlling the acceptance of the bid? She's the individual she
can accept her lowest bid and just go with it.
Okay, right. I mean I think that the assumption here is that
it's yeah, I think the גמרא Gemara assumes that if there's a
process of הכרזה hachrazah it means a process where the highest bid
was accepted and enough people were aware of it to have a
chance to bid. That's what the גמרא's Gemara assuming a process of
הכרזה hachrazah is about. So if there was that process, who cares
if she won the auction? It was a fair process and she
won. But she can put up for
sale any part of their estate. Yeah, well the court allowed it.
I know, that's what's crazy.
That's where the highest bid was accepted and enough people were aware
of it to have a chance to bid. That's what the גמרא's
Gemara assuming a process of הכרזה hachrazah is about. So if there
was that process, who cares if she won the auction? It was
a fair process and she won. But she can put up for
sale any part of their estate? Yeah, well the קרקעי. karkei. I
know, that's what's crazy about it, right? That's what I said, if
you're the orphan, I would preempt her and go to בית דין
Beis Din and say look, can we just figure out how we're
going to arrange this so we could be in control of the
situation, like we'll sell off this property, put some money in escrow,
have some account or whatever. I know. מוכרת שלא בבית דין mocheret
shelo b'Beis Din gives her an enormous amount of control. Maybe that's
a good thing to force the orphan to get on top of
it. Okay, so anyways, let's take a look. So היכי דמי, heichi
dami, אי דאכרוז, ei d'achruz, if there's been an announcement and a
fair process, so אמאי לא תזבון ולא כלום, amai lo tizbun velo
klum, why can she
not be the one who won the lottery? Or won the auction,
excuse me. אלא לאו דלא אכרוז, ella lav dela achruz, it must
be that we don't need this whole process to be gone through.
She can do a private deal. ולאצמה לא תזבון ולא כלום, ulatzmah
lo tizbun velo klum, and that's why she can't sell it to
herself. הא לאחר מאי דעבד עבד, ha l'acher mai de'avad avad, she
can sell it to another person without there being a big public
process and open process of an auction. So you see, it sounds
like you don't need it, right? Which is also deeply troubling. Oh
my gosh, she can just on her own pick which piece of
the estate she's going to sell off, decide how much she's going
to sell it for, maybe it's not even malicious, maybe she just
doesn't know the business and she's going to make this terrible deal,
right?
So the גמרא Gemara says we're talking about widows, oh, a widow.
But it just doesn't matter, even if it's not malicious, A, she
might not care for the orphans, they might not be her children,
and D, right, it's like,
what do you call it?
She might just do it out of ignorance. She's not aware about
how much of the estate is really worth, the piece of property
that she's selling.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, my father told me this is
going back decades, that there was a story about a case that
somebody saw in the newspaper, this woman was selling, again it was
some fancy car, Jaguar, something like that, Ferrari, for like $100. So
nobody answered it, everybody thought it was a mistake or a joke.
One guy went and actually what it turned out was
that the person who owned it died, and he left in his
will that his wife was the executor of the estate, but he
left in his will that the proceeds of it should go to
his mistress. So
the wife was selling it for $100! So he bought
it!
All right, so anyways, so the גמרא Gemara says, all right, so
it says, okay, it could have been, it could have gone to
the kids and she didn't like the kids, but okay, anyway. All
right, so the גמרא Gemara says, לעולם... le-olam...
that's a good story.
That is a good story. So הא לאחר מאי דעבד עבד, ha
l'acher mai de'avad avad, so it seems like you don't need a
process, because if you needed a process, she'd be entitled to bid
on it herself. The גמרא Gemara says, לא, לעולם דאכרוז. lo, le-olam
d'achruz. No, no, no, you need a public process when it's being
sold to another person. Okay, ודאמרי לה, ve-damri lah, but the reason
she can't pocket it for herself is because you say to her,
מאן שמליך, man shamlich, who is the one that assessed it for
you? Meaning, who did you buy it from? Look at רש"י. Rashi.
I mean, you put, took it out of your left pocket and
put it into your right pocket, even if the price set was
a fair price. Okay, so
if you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, he says the following,
the second narrow line, מאן שמליך, man shamlich, he says,
ממי קבלת מכירה זו? mimi kabalt mechira zu? לא מבית דין, lo
m'Beis Din, the court didn't sell it, ולא מיתמי, velo m'yasmei, the
orphans didn't sell it. You sold it to yourself. Okay, that's not
a sale, taking it out of one pocket and putting it into
the next.
לפיכך לא יצאה קרקע מרשות יתומים. le-fichach lo yatzah karka mereshus yesomim.
Right, I'm confusing you by talking about a Ferrari, but it's all
about land. Okay, the land did not go from, did not leave
them. So it's not, it doesn't bind not because the price wasn't
fair, but because for it to sort of like be a legitimate
transfer, there has to be two sides to the process. Okay, אהיכא
דשמא לאחריני, a-heicha d'shama l'achrinei, but if she sells it to others,
נפק מרשות יתומים שהרי נתנו לה חכמים רשות למכור. nafak mereshus yesomim
she-harei nasnu lah Chachamim reshus limkor. Okay, they gave her permission. So
basically, I mean, or you could have just said it's unseemly even
if there has been a fair price, it's still unseemly for her
to sell it to herself. But also just technically, you need two
sides to the transaction. Okay, but there would be a process of
הכרזה. hachrazah. You cannot have a sale without this public process. Okay,
כי הא דההוא גברא, ki ha d'hahu gavra, like the story of
a certain person, דאפקידו גביה כסא דיתמי, d'afkidu gabeih kassa d'yasmei, a
certain person was entrusted to him a... רש"י Rashi says it means
like fodder of the orphans, or רש"י Rashi also says it might
mean some type of coral of orphans.
Case of knowing they say a pocket of money or something?
I don't know, apparently not. אזל שמה לנפשיה. azal shamah l'nafsheih. So
he went ahead and now apparently this was a person that he
was the... like he was the executor of the estate, he was
like an אפוטרופוס apotropus or something, okay? It was his job to
sell off in order to pay for the expenses of the estate.
He liked this a lot. So he went ahead and he assessed
it for himself בארבע מאה זוזי, b'arbah me'ah zuzei, 400 zuz. And
he bought it for himself, and he gave the money to the
estate. יקר קם בשית מאה. yakar kam b'shis me'ah. Now it went
up in value, now it's worth 600 zuz. אתא לקמיה
דרבי אמי. ata l'kameih d'Rabbi Ami. He went in front of Rabbi
Ami. אמר ליה, amar leih, he said to him, מאן שמליך? man
shamlich? Who is the one that assessed it for you? Who'd you
buy it off of? You didn't buy it off of anyone, you
bought it off of yourself, it still belongs to the orphans. Okay.
Now, so bottom line is, והלכתא, v'hilchasa, what's the bottom line?
צריכה שבועה, tzrichah shevuah, she has to make a
שבועה. shevuah. No, I mean, I guess you could say what the
שבועה shevuah is about, maybe, maybe the שבועה shevuah is not just
about she hasn't been partially paid but that it was a fair
price or something. But again, she might just be ignorant. She could
take a שבועה shevuah that I sold it at the best price
I thought, right? But if but maybe she doesn't know enough to
sell it at a good price. So this does seem like she
has way too much latitude, right? I mean, שלא בבית דין shelo
be-veit din and she doesn't need הכרזה achrazah and how do you
know she's selling it at a good price? Who's who's protecting the
interests of the orphan, you know, it does seem very curious here
what's going on.
Oh yeah, curious because it's not clear who's supposed to get the
interest, the widow or the orphan.
Right. I mean, yeah, they both have legitimate interests, right?
Right. I mean, who are we trying to protect more?
Yeah. I mean, it sounds from these סוגיות sugyot that we're trying
to protect her the most, you know, but it does but then
you get to a point where you wonder if we've gone overboard,
right? All right.
Does he answer anything about, you know, what happens if she starts
partially doing it or not, right? What? We didn't answer anything about
what happens if she starts partially selling off her כתובה ketubah versus
fully selling off her כתובה, ketubah, right? We didn't answer that. That
kind of way?
Yeah, I mean, well presumably we פוסקין paskin לא כשמעון, lo k'Shimon,
we don't פוסקין paskin like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon, Okay. Okay, so
even though the גמרא Gemara didn't say והלכתא ve'hilchata we're just going
by that?
Right. Okay. Fine.
Now by the way תוספות Tosafot says, take a look at תוספות
Tosafot about this question of the שבועה, shevuah, אלא נראה לרבי ela
nireh le-Rabbi the last narrow line of the תוספות, Tosafot, אלא נראה
לרבי דבמכרת כתובה מיבעי ליה ela nireh le-Rabbi deve'mocheres kesuvah miba'ei lei
when a woman is selling off the property for the כתובה. kesuvah.
That's the question. דתחילה קודם גביית כתובה detechilah kodem geviyas kesuvah before
she starts collecting anything for the כתובה, kesuvah, משביעין אותה שלא עכבה
משל
בעלה כלום.
mashbi'in osah shelo ikvah mishel ba'alah
klum.
That's the שבועה shevuah that we know that the widow makes, which
is that none of the כתובה kesuvah has already been paid out
when her husband was alive. Okay, and that's we there's no question
she would make that, that's the standard שבועה shevuah she makes. ולאחר
שמכרה נכסים שלא בבית דין לגבות מהן כתובה מיבעי ליה. ule'achar shemocherah
nechasim shelo be'veit din ligbos me'hen kesuvah miba'ei lei. Now here's the
question. So she started with made her take an שבועה shevuah that
the כתובה kesuvah was not paid off in her husband's life, and
then she started selling off the estate to get the, you know,
to have the כתובה kesuvah paid off. And now we want to
know אם חוזר ומשביעין אותה שלא גבתה יותר im chozer umashbi'in osah
shelo gavseh yoser whether you, you know, make her take another שבועה
shevuah that she didn't collect more than she says she's collected in
her process of selling off the estate. Like she says well I
sold off part of the estate in order to get half the
כתובה kesuvah paid off. So you believe her or do you have
to make her take an שבועה shevuah of exactly how much, right?
There's two questions. One is did the husband prepay it while he
was still alive and then the other question once the process begins
is how much of the כתובה kesuvah have I actually already pocketed
in my process of selling off the estate? That's issue number that's
possibility number one, that it's a שבועה shevuah during the process. ועוד
אומר רבי, ve'od omer Rabbi, רבי also says, דהאי שבועה דמיבעי ליה
לא כפירוש הקונטרס שלא גבתה יותר. dehai shevuah demiba'ei lei lo k'perush
hakuntreis shelo gavseh yoser. Really, the שבועה shevuah we're talking here is
not an שבועה shevuah about that she did
not overpay herself for the כתובה. kesuvah. אלא מיבעי ליה ela miba'ei
lei here's the question, אם משביעין אותה שלא זלזלה בנכסים im mashbi'in
osah shelo zilzelah banechasim
whether you make her take an שבועה shevuah that she did not
deal, you know, what's a good translation of זלזלה, zilzelah,
like carelessly, she did not squander, she did not deal carelessly with
the property. וכן מוכיח מדקאמר תיבעי לך הכרזה vechen mochiach mideka'amar tiva'ei
lach achrazah because what's the relevance of a שבועה shevuah to this
process of announcement and הכרזה, achrazah, right? שבועה shevuah is whether you've
been paid, הכרזה achrazah is whether you're getting a good price. So
דהוי נמי שלא תזלזל dehavei nami shelo tizazel so ultimately what we're
talking about here is what the שבועה shevuah is that she's getting
that she's treating, you know, she's not dealing with it irresponsibly. Okay,
so we say she makes a שבועה shevuah that she dealt with
it responsibly, but she does not have to do a process of
הכרזה. achrazah. Again, the process is it's all very nice, but maybe
she doesn't know enough, you know, to get the best price she
could get. Okay, so there really is an interesting question here that
she has this enormous amount of latitude and even if we make
her take a שבועה shevuah that she's being careful, right? How
you know, how does that really ensure that the heirs' interests are
being protected? Not so clear. Let's take a look now at the
next משנה. mishna. אלמנה שהיתה כתובתה מאתים ומוכרת שוה מנה במאתים. almanah
shehayesa kesuvassah masayim umocheres shaveh maneh bemasayim. So her כתובה kesuvah was
200, we're פוסקין paskin like the חכמים chachamim that she can sell
it off without בית דין be-veit din even for the base כתובה,
kesuvah, not just for the מזונות mezonot or the lump sum כתובה
kesuvah I should say.
So let's say she sells more than this standard?
No, it was 200, now she went ahead and she sold, yeah,
she went ahead and she sold a piece of the estate
that normally on a normally on a normal market would have only
fetched 100, but she made a real deal or she found a
dupe, one of the other, anyway, but she managed to get 200,
200 for it. Okay. So now here's the question. Does she say
well it was only worth 100, I get to collect the other
100, or do the orphans get to say what are you talking
about? You got 200 dollars out of the estate. Goodbye, you're done.
Okay, so presumably obviously it would be the second, she got paid,
who cares whether she made a
good... או שווים מאתיים במנה. O shavim matayim be-maneh. She actually made
a bad deal. She sold a piece of the estate worth two
hundred for a hundred. Does she get to say, I only got
a hundred paid out and I deserve another hundred? So either way
נגבתה כתובתה, Nigveta ketuvata, either way she is done. In the first
case she actually pocketed the two hundred, we very much appreciate that
you made a good deal, but you pocketed the two hundred. And
in the other case it is like you wasted our money, so
you should not be entitled to squander our money. You sold a
piece of property worth two hundred, that is considered like you got
fully paid.
She is losing out really, or like she is.
Right, I mean based on this she clearly, you are right, has
no incentive to, she has all the incentive in the world and
that partially answers our previous discussion to make sure that she is
getting a fair price. She does not have any incentive to get
a better price than the going price, that is true, but she
certainly has an incentive to make sure that she is not getting
cheated. Okay, so that at least partly answers the previous question.
הייתה כתובתה מנה מכרה שווה מנה ודינר במנה. Hayta ketuvata maneh makhra
shaveh maneh ve-dinar be-maneh. Her כתובה Ketubah was a hundred and she
sold a piece of the estate worth a hundred and twenty-five, a
דינר Dinar is twenty-five, a hundred and twenty-five for a hundred. Okay,
so basically she basically had now here this is different because the
piece of the estate she sold, she was not entitled to that
whole piece of property. Right, you understand, in the first scenario she
got cheated but she sold a piece of property worth two hundred,
she was entitled to that whole piece of property. Here she started
with a piece of property worth a hundred and twenty-five, she only
had a debt of a hundred, she was not entitled to that
whole piece of property and nevertheless she sold it. So in this
case מכרה בטל, Makhra batel, the sale is void. Okay, because she
sold a property, now you do not just say the twenty-five is
void, you say the whole thing is void because she sold a
piece of property that she did not have rights to the whole
property.
I guess it is like you cannot necessarily divide it, right?
All right, so we will discuss it in the גמרא. Gemara. אפילו
היא אומרת אחזיר דינר ליורשים, Afilu hi omeret akhzir dinar li-yorshim, even
if she says wait wait wait, I will pay them back the
twenty-five dollars. I mean I took a piece of property worth, I
am saying twenty-five but whatever, multiplied by a hundred or a thousand,
whatever, but anyway I will pay the heirs back
the twenty-five thousand dollars extra that the property was worth. Okay, yes,
I took too big of a piece of property but rather than
voiding this whole sale and having me to start again from the
beginning and I made a good deal and it is going to
be hard to sell it and I need the money, let me
just give them back the extra amount of the value of the
estate that I took from them. Tough luck, you sold a piece
of property that was not yours that you did not have a
right to sell.
Why is this different than the case in which she sells a
piece of land worth two hundred?
Because then her debt was two hundred so she had a right
to sell the whole piece of land.
So here her debt
was, no, the scenario mentioned was that it was
a hundred and she sold a piece of land worth a hundred
and twenty-five, worth more than her debt. Okay, of course this is
very tricky because how do you get exactly the piece of land
worth exactly your debt? In most cases you are going to be
over or under.
Is not all these assets anyway mortgaged to pay her?
Yeah,
but that does not mean she can sell a piece of land
that is bigger than what her debt is. All right, רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל אומר לעולם מכרה קיים עד שתהא שם כדי שתשתייר בשדה
בת תשעה קבין. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer le-olam makhra kayam ad
she-tehe sham kedei she-tishtayer ba-sadeh bat tish'ah kabbin. The sale is always
valid unless the overage was so much or the underage I guess
from depending on which perspective, but the amount she got cheated out
of was a piece of field so big כדי שתשתייר בשדה בת
תשעה קבין Kedei she-tishtayer ba-sadeh bat tish'ah kabbin the size of nine
קב. Kav. I do not know exactly what that is. ובגינה בת
חצי קב U-ve-ginah bat khatzi kav and if it is not a
wheat field, a grain field, but it is like a more of
a garden, a vegetable garden, then it is a much smaller amount
of significance, a half of a קב. Kav. וכדברי רבי עקיבא בת
רובע U-kh-divrei Rabbi Akiva bat rova according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
a quarter. Okay,
so anyway basically he says it that it cannot be so precise
in the size of the field. If
it is a little over it is fine and the logic is
that if it is a big enough chunk that you went over,
you could subdivide the property.
Right, I could not have what do you mean, I could not
have sold ninety-eight percent of this field and not sold the other
two percent. So what they are saying is you know what, that
is a good point, so a little bit over is okay. But
if it is so much over that the extra amount could have
existed as a separate piece of property, then you should have subdivided
it and drawn the line elsewhere.
Okay, so apparently a twenty-five דינר Dinar piece of land is a
viable chunk?
Exactly, well depends, no, he says it is based on the actual
acreage. That is what he is saying, it is not a דינר
Dinar it is based on the acreage.
He is not discussing here the quality of the land, right?
In other words, like you know.
Yes, that
is why רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says it
is not about a dollar value, it is about the acreage. The
acreage determines whether that piece of land is subdividable.
But meaning he is not saying that if you had a choice
of land, do not sell the Manhattan real estate versus the,
it would all work out. The bottom line is that you can
sell what is equal to the value of your property if it
cannot be subdivided.
All right, yes, fine. I got it.
General rules about זיבורית. Ziburi.
Right, we usually from זיבורית, Ziburi, but he's not, they're not going
into that.
Right, right. היתה כתובתה ארבע מאה
זוז. Hayta ktubata arba me'ah zuz. Now her כתובה ketubah 400 זוז.
zuz. ומכרו לזה במנה ולזה במנה ולאחרון יפה מנה ודינר
במנה. Umachru leze b'maneh uleze b'maneh ule'acharon yafeh maneh vedinar b'maneh. So
it was 400 זוז. zuz. So she sold off actually it's missing
one one of the guys here. She sold off to Reuven a
field of 100, to Shimon a field of 100, to Levi a
field of 100, and to Yehuda she made this mistake. She sold
a field of 125 for 100. Okay, so אחרון בטל ושל כולן
קיים. acharon batel veshel kulan kayam. So only the last sale is
void, all the previous sales are good and she still has 300
of her 400 כתובה ketubah sold. Okay, but bottom line the point
of the end of the המשנה Mishnah is she cannot sell whatever
price she gets for it. She's not entitled to sell a piece
of property that is worth more than her outstanding debt unless it
is not possible to, like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel position makes the most sense, unless it's not possible to subdivide
it into a smaller piece. Okay, let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. מאי שנא שוה מאתיים במנה? Mai shna shaveh matayim b'maneh?
Why when she sells 200 for 100 is her כתובה ketubah considered
paid off? דאמרי לה את הפסדת. De'amri la at hifsadet. They say
to her look it's your loss. That was a piece of property
worth the amount of money. We do not have to suffer, you
know, from your bad business deals. And therefore you have basically forfeited,
you know, the rest of your, the rest of your debt, which
again as we pointed out is a very good reason for her
to get some good advice in terms of to
make sure or go to the
בית דין Beis Din which is what you know right exactly to
make sure that she's not underselling. But שוה מנה במאתיים נמי תימא?
Shaveh maneh b'matayim nami tema? So why not say in the reverse?
If she sells 100 for 200, let her say to them אנא
ארווחנא, ana arvachna, I took a piece of the estate only worth
100, like even make a, you know, either look at the amount
of money I pocket or look at the size of the property
I sold. If when I sold 200 for 100 you're going to
look at the size of the property,
so when I sold 100 for 200 look at the size of
the property worth 100 and the extra money I made was my
own good business dealings and it goes into my pocket, it's not
payment for the כתובה. ketubah. So אמר רב נחמן אמר רב בר
אבוה כאן שנה רבי הכל לבעל המעות,
Amar Rav Nachman amar Rav bar
Avuha kan shana Rebbi hakol l'ba'al hama'ot, right, which is you know
everybody, all goes to the person who... what is like the golden
rule? The guy with the gold makes the rules. Everyone, it all
goes to the person with the money. Okay, which means that if
you basically send somebody off to the marketplace and you give them
money then you, any any deal he makes you get you benefit
from, not not him. Okay, so let's take a look at the
example.
Which this also should depend on which we say the נכסים בחזקת
אלמנה...
nechasim
b'chezkat ha'almanot...
maybe, maybe, that's a good point. דתניא, Detanya, like we've done a
ברייתא. beraita. הוסיפו לו אחת יתירה הכל לשליח דברי רבי יהודה. Hosifu
lo achat yeteirah hakol lashaliach divrei Rebbi Yehuda. Basically here's the case
is that okay, that, hold on let me just double check רש"י.
Rashi.
Okay, right. So basically you send somebody to the store and you
give them 20 bucks to buy you know, I don't know, to
buy some apples and they go ahead and he buys a bushel
of apples and the storekeeper says, "Here, take an extra one." Okay,
so when he says, "Take an extra one," who gets to keep
it? The guy who who you who went to the store? Does
he have to give it back to you because you're the one
who sent him? Is it part of the sale and it goes
to the person who who's paying for it? Or was it a
gift to you? "Oh here here's an apple, keep it," and it
was a gift to you that you're the guy who showed up
in the store. So let's take a look. הוסיפו לו אחת יתירה,
Hosifu lo achat yeteirah, they gave him an extra apple. והכל לשליח
דברי רבי יהודה. Vehakol lashaliach divrei Rebbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
says keep it, it's a gift to you, you get to keep
it. רבי יוסי אומר חולקין, Rebbi Yossi omer cholkin, split it with
the owner who sent you to the store. And I mean the,
you know, the guy with the money. והתניא, Vehatanya, but it was
taught in a ברייתא beraita רבי יוסי אומר הכל לבעל המעות, Rebbi
Yossi omer hakol l'ba'al hama'ot, you have to give it all back
to the guy who sent you with the money to the store.
So אמר רמי בר חמא לא קשיא, Amar Rami bar Chama lo
kashya, it's not difficult. כאן בדבר שיש לו קצבה כאן בדבר שאין
לו קצבה. Kan b'davar sheyesh lo kitzva kan b'davar she'ein lo kitzva.
It depends, is there a fixed amount or not a fixed amount?
If basically there's a fixed amount, you know it's like I don't
know, 12 eggs is for a dollar, so an extra one is
clearly a gift. It's not part of the sale, right? There's a
fixed price for a fixed amount. If however there's some non-fixed nature
of it, there's some amount of like negotiation or something and he
says, "How much should I sell this to you? Oh let's, you
know what, that sort of like let's, you know, I'm thinking of
an example." You know if if you ever buy the fruit from
those guys on the sidewalk, you know and sometimes they'll like, you
know, weigh stuff or whatever, they'll like throw in some extra just
to make sure that like they're, you know, they're giving you more,
you know, they're not underselling you the weight, right? So in that
type of a case it's like they're doing it because that's part
of the sale. You know, they want to make sure they're not
underselling you. It's not like it was a clear you had what
you paid for and here's an extra. This became part of what
was paid for, okay? So שאין לו קצבה ein lo kitzva could
also mean there's like a negotiated amount. If there's a negotiated amount
and we agree on a price of five dollars and after we
agree on a price of five dollars I say, "Here, take another
one," so okay, that's sort of part of the negotiation. That becomes
part of what I sold you, it doesn't become a gift.
Okay. After every
שוק.
shuk.
Really? Okay.
Always sell like that. Great. But not if they like— "Oh, I
like you, you know, here take an extra."
Fine. So that's the issue. Okay. Come the the case of שיש
לו קצבה sheyeish lo kitzva come the case of שאין לו קצבה.
she'ein lo kitzva. So if there's a fixed price, fixed amount, and
they give you an extra, that's a gift. Then you get to
keep it or then you maybe you split it with the owner.
Okay? It's a gift to you, but it's also a gift to
the owner. But if it's not a fixed amount, then it becomes
it's somewhat of a negotiated or it becomes part of the sale,
then it all goes to the owner. Okay? So therefore, how's that
relevant? So that's relevant because the sale of land is always an
אין לו קצבה, ein lo kitzva, is always a negotiated amount. There's
never a fixed price on the sale of land. So therefore, if
she manages to get $200 for this piece of property, even if
it otherwise would have been assessed for $100, it's not a gift
to her, it's money that goes to the estate. It's part of
the price, it's part of the, you know, payment for the property.
And since it's money that goes to the estate, then, then the
estate got the full amount and then she's paid off her full
כתובה. ketubah. She didn't get it as some gift. It's not some
prize for her. Okay? Which makes a lot of sense. אמר פפא,
Amar Pappa, הלכתא, hilchata, the הלכה halacha is דבר שיש לו קצבה
חולקים. davar sheyeish lo kitzva cholkim. If it's a fixed amount and
a clear price and you were given something extra, then you split
it between the שליח shaliach and the owner. דבר שאין לו קצבה,
davar she'ein lo kitzva, if there is not a clear amount fixed,
then הכל לבעל המעות hakol leba'al hama'ot and the person who's paying
gets it because then it becomes part of the transaction. מאי קמשמע
לן? mai kamashma lan? What are you telling me? We just gave
this answer. So you're telling me שינויא דשנינן שינויא הוא. shinuyah deshanynan
shinuyah hu. The answer we gave was a good answer. Okay? That
that explains the difference and that also explains what's going on in
our משנה. mishna. She negotiated a price. In the end, this was
not a gift to her. This was the price for the field,
so the money goes to the estate. Okay. איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu,
they asked the following
question: אמרי ליה זבין לי ליתכא. amri leh zavin li litkha. So
אזיל וזבין ליה כורא. azil vezavin leh kura. Oh, wait, this is
going to circle back to our case in the משנה. mishna. You
tell a guy, go buy for me a ליתכא, litkha, which is
a how much is it?
A half of
a כור kor ואזיל וזבין ליה כורא. ve'azil vezavin leh kura. He
goes and he buys you a כור. kor. Okay.
מאי? mai? What, how do we interpret this? מוסיף על דבריו הוי?
mosif al devarav havei? Do we say he added to his words?
He the ליתכא מיקנא. litkha mikna. Do we say he did what
you told him to do? He bought a half of a bushel.
Okay? He also bought another half of a bushel. But the first
half bushel he was listening to you and he was your agent
and that's a binding sale. The other's he was out on his
own and he has to pay you back for it or who
knows what? Okay, but that wasn't— or eat it or whatever. Anyway,
the point is that he actually was your agent for that half
and that sale is binding.
או דלמא מעביר על דבריו הוי? o dilma ma'avir al devarav havei?
No,
when you went and bought a bushel, you were completely disregarding what
I told you to do וליתכא נמי לא קני, velitkha nami lo
kani, and he doesn't even— the half bushel sale is void because
he was not following my my agency in that transaction.
That's sort of like this our case?
Well, that's exactly why the גמרא gemara is raising it. אמר רב
יעקב מפקוט, Amar Rav Ya'akov me-Pakot, Rav Ya'akov from Pakot said משמיה
דרבינא mishmei de-Ravina in the name of Ravina, תא שמע, ta shema,
come hear. אמר בעל הבית לשלוחו. Amar ba'al habayit lishlucho. So here's
a principle of מעילה. me'ilah. The principle of מעילה me'ilah is that
you only bring a קרבן מעילה korban me'ilah if you transgress it
בשוגג, beshogeg, unwittingly. You don't— we're not aware that the the stuff
that you're eating and benefiting from belongs to הקדש. hekdesh. The other
interesting part of מעילה me'ilah is that it's one of the only
places in הלכה halacha that we say יש שליח לדבר עבירה, yeish
shaliach ledvar aveirah, which is that even though somebody is doing my
agency and I'm not the one who transgresses, if he's unwitting and
I'm unwitting and we're all unwitting, it's like I did it. So
I basically go ahead and I tell דב Dov here to take
this here, דב, Dov, why don't you put out some of these
nice chunks of meat to my guests? And I give it to
him and he puts it out to my guests. It just happens
that I wasn't aware and he wasn't aware, nobody was aware that
this was some nice קרבן הקדש korban hekdesh meat. Okay? So even
though דב Dov is the one that's putting it out to them
and they're the ones that are eating it, so I'm not the
one that ever did anything wrong with it, like I just— אין
שליח לדבר עבירה. ein shaliach ledvar aveirah. No, since it's all being
done on my behalf and nobody is and nobody is witting, is
the word witting? Nobody is unwitting, everybody
is unwitting.
Anyway, anyway, in that case, I'm the one that did מעילה. me'ilah.
Okay?
Now, here's the case. אמר בעל הבית לשלוחו, Amar ba'al habayit lishlucho,
I say to my agent, "תן להם
חתיכה לאורחים, ten lahem chaticha la'orchim, go give all of the guests
a nice little piece of meat." וכל שהוא קדשים, vechol shehu kodshim,
and it's
קדשים. kodshim. והוא אומר, vehu omer, and he says to them, "טלו
שתים, telu shtayim, eh, you know what?
Everybody take two pieces.
Okay? Don't tell him, take two pieces." והן, vehen, and they went
ahead ונטלו שלש, venatlu shalosh, and they took three pieces.
So כולם מעלו, kulam ma'alu, everybody gets מעילה. me'ilah. Okay? I get
מעילה me'ilah for the first piece they took, because then everybody was
acting on my behalf. דב Dov here gets... מעילה Me'ila for the
second piece because the second piece they were acting on his initiative,
and they get מעילה Me'ila for the third piece because that was
on their own initiative. Okay? So everybody gets מעילה.
Me'ila. Okay. So that's for the שוגג, shogeg, what's it called outright?
מזיד. Meizid. No, no, that's not what I meant. In other words,
you take like מעילה Me'ila is only בשוגג? beshogeg?
Well, you know, I mean it's it's a לאו lav and you
get מלקות malkus or whatever, but you don't bring the קרבן. korban.
The הלכה halacha is about מעילה Me'ila and קרבן מעילה. korban Me'ila.
And the הלכה halacha that יש שליח לדבר עבירה yeish shliach lidvar
aveira only apply in the case of שוגג. shogeg. If you know
what you're doing, then you're acting on your own. You're not acting
as as an extension of me. But if everybody is unwitting about
what's wrong here, then they're acting as an extension of the person
who initiated it.
Okay? Why didn't he teach מעילה Me'ila first? Who knows? Who knows?
We're getting there. We're circling around. Okay. אי אמרת Ee amrat בשלמא
bishlama מוסיף על דבריו הוי, mosif al devarav havei, if you say
that when you go ahead and you increase the amount, you're do
the first part you're doing what you were told and the next
you're on your you're adding your own initiative. So משום הכי mishum
hachi בעל הבית Ba'al Habayis מעל, ma'al, that's why I was מועל
mo'el because the first piece of meat everybody took they were it
was part of my agency. It was part of, you know, you
know, my initiative. אלא אי אמרת Ela ee amrat מעביר על דבריו
הוי, ma'avir al devarav havei, but when somebody increases then they're just
the the agent when the agent increases he's off on his own
for the whole thing, בעל הבית אמאי מעל? Ba'al Habayis amai ma'al?
So why did I do anything wrong? The agent when he said
two, he was going out on his own on the whole thing.
דתנן, Detnan, we taught השליח עשה שליחותו, hashaliach asa shlichuso, when the
messenger the the agent does what he was appointed to do, בעל
הבית Ba'al Habayis מעל, ma'al, that's when the person who sent him
does מעילה. Me'ila. לא עשה שליחותו, Lo asa shlichuso, השליח hashaliach מעל,
ma'al, if not, then it's all on the שליח's shaliach head. So
you see that even though the שליח shaliach added, he is considered
to only on it be on his own regarding the part he's
adding, not being on his own regarding the whole part. So the
גמרא Gemara says הכא במאי עסקינן hacha bemai askinan what are we
talking about דאמר להו de'amar lehu that the, so you're right. In
general, you'd be right. The שליח shaliach if he went and just
said two, he'd be out on his own and it would not
be on the בעל הבית Ba'al Habayis at all. But here's what
happened. The שליח shaliach didn't just say take two. He said the
following to the guests. He said דאמר להו de'amar lehu טלו אחת
מדעתו של בעל הבית ואחת מדעתי. telu achas mida'ato shel Ba'al Habayis
ve'achas mida'ati. Okay, he said to them explicitly, guys, the owner says
you can each take one, so go ahead and take one, that's,
you know, but let me tell you, it'll be on me, you
go ahead and take a second one. So he specifically sort of,
you know, identified that there was a different thing. He was giving
them one, you know, for the owner and the other he was
giving them on his own. But if he had just said here,
the owner asked me to give you all two, then he would
be considered to have been totally going against what he was told
to do, right? More is not the is not the same plus.
More is going totally against and then the whole thing would be
considered to be on his own.
So בעל הבית Ba'al Habayis is not מועל mo'el on any of
this, even on the first one?
If the שליח shaliach goes out on his own, correct.
Even though like one of them was from the בעל הבית Ba'al
Habayis anyway and they
Yeah, but if the שליח shaliach did not say one on his
account, one on my account, he just said here, the owner said
everybody,
but you said he did say one on each account.
Then then that's when the בעל הבית Ba'al Habayis is מועל. mo'el.
The בעל הבית Ba'al Habayis is מועל mo'el when he says, hey
guys, take one because the בעל הבית Ba'al Habayis said you could
all take one. And then they said, oh, well we're still hungry.
He said fine fine, go ahead and take two. So in that
case, it was only the second one that he was acting on
his own initiative. The first one he was clearly acting as part
of the בעל הבית. Ba'al Habayis. And they're both מועל. mo'el. Yeah,
fine. Okay. The only but the גמרא Gemara is saying that if
you just said, hey guys, you can all take two, and he
was presenting that as as if he was doing it for the
בעל הבית, Ba'al Habayis, and he has totally gone against what the
בעל הבית Ba'al Habayis said, and he's totally off on his own.
And if he told them to take two but they only ended
up taking one, then is it that the בעל הבית Ba'al Habayis
is מועל? mo'el?
That's a cute question, I don't know. Okay, תא שמע. Ta shema.
Okay, the שקלא וטריא shakla vetarya is fast. Okay, now,
תא שמע, Ta shema, now we get back to our case. היתה
כתובתה מנה ומכרה שוה מנה ודינר במנה. Hayesa kesubasa maneh umachra shaveh
maneh vedinar bemaneh.
So her כתובה kesuba was worth a hundred and she sold the
estate of a hundred and twenty-five for a hundred. מכרה בטל, Mechrato
batel, the whole thing is void. Now why is the whole thing
void? Why not say that the part of it that was at
least worth the hundred should be valid? מאי לאו Mai lav דזבין
שוה מנה ודינר במנה ודינר? dezavin shaveh maneh vedinar bemaneh vedinar? Okay,
now, the גמרא Gemara also assumes though the following, that it was
actual, actually,
that it was not that she got cheated out of the deal.
She actually sold a piece of property worth a hundred and twenty-five
for a hundred and twenty-five. So what does it mean במנה? bemaneh?
What does it mean she sold it for a hundred? It means
מנה שלה, maneh shela, it means she sold it to pay off
her her her debt of a hundred, the money that the hundred
that was owed her, right? Here's how it's reading the משנה. Mishna.
She sold a hundred and twenty-five, not that she pocketed a hundred
dollars. She sold it for a hundred and twenty-five, but she sold
it in order to collect her hundred dollars. Okay, so that's how
it's reading it, but she sold a hundred and twenty-five for a
hundred and twenty-five. The only problem was she wasn't inside of entitled
to sell that big of a property, but she got the right
price.
Okay. It's the right price, but she could have taken a hundred,
she could
give back twenty-five to the
That's the question, right.
Okay, ומאי אפילו? Umai afillu? What does it mean even? Even if
she says I'll give back twenty-five. אפילו היא אומרת אחזיר את הדינר
ליורשים, Afillu hee omeres achzir es hadinar layorshim, so בדינא מיקרקעי? bedina
mekarkei? So what do you mean? Of course she has to give
back the twenty-five. What do you mean even if she says she'll
give back the twenty-five? She got a hundred and twenty-five, she’s only
owed a hundred, she gives back the others. She says no. Let’s
say she says I got a hundred and twenty-five, I sold the
whole piece, what I’m going to do is, you say oh we
don’t have land, I will take the twenty-five and buy you a
piece of land with it. Okay? So I got a good price,
I didn’t get cheated, I’m only getting paid for what was owed
to me. I had to sell the whole piece of property. I
got an extra twenty-five. Not only will I give it to you
in cash, I’ll buy you another piece of property. Okay, that’s how
we’re going to read the משנה. Mishna. Nevertheless, we say tough. Doesn’t
matter, you sold too big of a piece of property. So וקתני
מכרה בטל Vektani mekhra batel and it says it's void. So the
only explanation for that is that she was not entitled to sell
that, that even though she was מוסיף mosif on her sort of
license, on her agency, she was empowered to sell a hundred, she
sold a hundred and twenty-five, we don’t say the hundred that she
sold was valid, the twenty-five was not valid. We say the whole
thing was not valid. So doesn’t that prove our case that when
you exceed your agency, you’re totally out on your own? So the
גמרא Gemara says, I mean, they’re so interesting how many cases in
like the real world you could apply this to like in work
or whatever, you know, you’re told to do one thing and then
you often... how much are you totally out on your own? Anyway,
אמר רב הונא בריה דרב נתן, Amar Rav Huna brei de-Rav Natan,
לא, lo, that’s not the case. The case is not she sold
a hundred and twenty-five for a hundred and twenty-five and the issue
is that and that extra twenty-five she did something extra. The problem
is בדאושיה, bedoshaya, what we thought the משנה Mishna meant, that she
undersold it. It was worth a hundred and twenty-five and she undersold
it for a hundred. And because she undersold it, that’s why it’s
void. It’s void because she got cheated out of it. Okay? It’s
void because she undersold. And if she undersells and that’s a and
then we could say fine, you’re just going to get paid based
on what it was worth, she sold two hundred for a hundred,
but we can say we’re done with you because you know it
was worth two hundred, fine, you lost. But here you undersold it
and we’re the ones losing, we the יורשים, yorshim, right? Because you
undersold it and that extra twenty-five was money that we deserved. Okay?
So that’s why they said that it’s בטל batel is because it
was undersold. But if it actually was sold for the right price
but too much was sold, maybe we say the first hundred was
legitimate and the second hundred... that’s the only thing that was acting
out of, you know, she was not empowered to do. But for
the first hundred she was empowered and that might continue to be
legitimate. So we’ll continue with this question about when you exceed your
agency what the consequences are, we’ll continue that tomorrow.
Is this the first time we’re seeing this תלמוד Talmud is conceptualizing
her selling the estate off for מזונות mezonot as a שליחות shlichut
in terms of שליחות? shlichut?
That’s yes, yes, she’s
a שליח shaliach for the יורשים. yorshim. Right.